Guide to the Oral History of the American Left Collection OH.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Oral History of the American Left Collection
1940-2011
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
OH.002
65.04 Linear Feet in 14 record cartons, 22 manuscript boxes, 19 cassette boxes, 3 half manuscript boxes, 1 small cassette box, 11 small flat boxes, 20 long card boxes, 1 media box, 1 card box, 1 small card box, 1 shared cassette box, and 1 folder in a shared manuscript box
66 kilobytes in 1 document
The Tamiment Library at New York University established the Oral History of the American Left in 1976 in order to collect and preserve the memories of veteran activists. These interviews describe seven decades of Left politics from the 1910s through the 1970s. They document the full spectrum of left politics in the twentieth century, including socialism, Communism, anarchism, Trotskyism, and the New Left. There are interviews with both leaders and rank-and-file activists.
Conditions Governing Access
Unless otherwise noted, materials are open without restrictions. Any limitations on access, as stipulated in an interviewee's release form, are noted at the interview or series level.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
From its inception, the Oral History of the American Left was an assembled collection with a diverse provenance. The majority of the interviews, particularly in Series I, were collected by the Oral History of American Left for deposit at the Tamiment Library. At the same time, OHAL solicited and accepted recordings from scholars, filmmakers, activists, and other likeminded individuals who were not affiliated with the project. OHAL staff actively took interviews between 1976-1985. The collection of interviews by OHAL and Tamiment Library continued through the late 2000s at a diminished pace. The collection also contains materials that were created or collected by the Tamiment Institute before the establishment of OHAL. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1976.001, 2004.026, 2010.002, 2018.050, and 2018.072.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into nine series: 1. Oral History of the American Left Main Series, 2. Fred Zimring Interviews, 3. Reynold Hills Project Interviews, 4. Filmmakers' Tapes and Transcripts, 5. Tamiment Institute Tapes, 6. Aleine Austin Tapes regarding Monthly Review and Highlander Folk School, 7. Restricted Interviews, 8. Higley Hill, 9. Rose Leopold, 10. Radio Free Maine Tapes, and 11. Remembering Emma.
Historical Note
New York University's Tamiment Library established the Oral History of the American Left (OHAL) in 1976. The purpose of this project was to expand the archive's documentation of radicalism and labor by recording the memories of veteran activists before they were lost. The founders of OHAL were working within the milieu of "new social history" and were intent on using the Oral History of the American Left to collect stories from groups often underrepresented in traditional historical narratives including rank and file activists, women, and ethnic minorities. The project founders, by their own admission, were a part of a revival of interest in folkloric community histories and captivated by the ability of the recorded interview to bring these stories to life. They also were cognizant of the interviewer's role in shaping an oral history, and the interviewers' own activism is also frequently on display. As such, decades later, the early interviews of the collection not only give insight into the experiences of activists from the 1910s-1960s, but illuminate the psychology of the Left during the Reagan era.
Paul Buhle was the director of the project from its founding, and was its most prolific interviewer. Other staff included Roger Keeran who was co-director in the early years and Jon Bloom who joined the project in 1977 to work as an interviewer, coordinator, and fundraiser. Additional OHAL staff in the 1980s included interviewer and project coordinator Ruth F. Prago, interviewer Bea Lemisch, and indexer Ameila Green.
Interviewing began with a series of small grants provided by the Rabinowitz and Bronson Cutting Foundations. The New Jersey Historical Commission provided funding in 1978 to support interviews on radicalism in New Jersey between 1930 and 1960. Later, Ruth F. Prago developed the idea to start a radio series based on interviews held for the OHAL collection. Together with Pacifica Radio the project received a one-year grant from the New York State Council for the Humanities to conduct interviews with twenty-five women about radicalism during the 1930s. Radio producers used these interviews to create the radio series "Grandma was an Activist," first broadcast in 1983. OHAL received major funding in 1982–1983 from the National Endowment for the Humanities. This support enabled Paul Buhle to build a comprehensive collection of oral histories regarding ethnic-immigrant radicalism, its press, and fraternal organizations. The NEH grant also enabled OHAL to collect hundreds of hours of interviews made by filmmakers on American anarchism, the Hollywood blacklist, the Communist Party, the Columbia University student strike of 1968, and other subjects.
From its founding, OHAL was intended to be a comprehensive document of the experiences of the members of the Left in the United States, and it was assumed that the collection would continue to grow over time. Tamiment Library continued to conduct interviews and collect interviews from third parties through the 1990s and into the early 2010s.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Audiovisual materials that have not been preserved may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact NYU Special Collections (special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596) with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Materials
Guide to the Oral History of the American Left, edited by Paul Buhle and Jonathan Bloom, is cataloged with Tamiment Library's bibliographic collections and provides insight into the goals and considerations at OHAL's founding and a history of the collection up to 1984. The project's newsletter, filed with Tamiment Library's serials, similarly gives context for the creation and collection of OHAL's earliest materials.
Paul Buhle Papers (TAM 171)
Scope and Contents
The Oral History of the American Left documents the broad range of experiences on the left, with a focus on underrepresented voices, particularly between 1910 and 1980. The Main Series (Series 1) is particularly sweeping in the topics that it documents, but a set of prominent topics emerge representing the interests of OHAL staff members in the early years of the collection. These include immigrant/ethnic radicalism, labor, women's history, radical newspapers, fraternal organizations, and student radicalism. The earliest interviews were done to collect the memories of men and women who could recall the 1910s-1920s. Later interviews document the effects of the Russian Revolution on the Left in the United States, the formation of social and cultural institutions by the "New Immigrant" groups, the history of socialism and anarchism, the relationship between the "Old Left" and "New Left," and Communist activism in the United States. There is also an analysis of the regional development of Left movements in the United States. OHAL interviewed representative figures from the Jewish, Finnish, Slovenian, Greek, Hungarian, Polish, Italian, Ukrainian, Lithuanian, African American, Japanese, Scandinavian, and Spanish Left. For many of these interviews, there is a focus on how ethnic identity and political identity interacted and how non-English-language presses and fraternal organizations preserved this identity in the United States. The cultural experiences of Yiddish-speaking Jews are particularly represented in this regard. Paul Buhle took a sizable amount of interviews related to the relationship between Yiddish-language literature and culture and Communist and socialist political organizations and newspapers.
The collection also documents the factionalism of the Left in the mid-20th century United States. Rank and file members and leaders alike comment on the conflicts between the Communist Party of the USA and different socialist and Trotskyist organizations, analyzing matters of theory and the personalities that drove the splits. The Johnson-Forest Tendency and CLR James receive particular attention. Other political parties/factions addressed include the the Socialist Party, Workers Party, Socialist Workers Party, and the American Labor Party. The CP's role in the period is examined in depth, both by members and opponents, especially during the 1930s. The interviews taken to support "Grandma Was an Activist" provide insight into the experiences of women activists during the period.
The collection includes several interviews with participants of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, the US component of the International Brigades which fought in the Spanish Civil War. There are other interviews documenting the long tenure of Jasper McLevy, Socialist Party Mayor of Bridgeport, Connecticut from 1933-1957. Organizations discussed in other interviews include the Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), Workmens' Circle, International Labor Defense, National Lawyers Guild, the Southern Negro Youth Congress, and the Yidisher Kultur Farband (YKUF), among many others. The labor movement and the operations of different political parties and factions within labor unions are also frequently addressed. The International Ladies Garment Workers Union (ILGWU) and the needle trades are particularly well represented in this regard.
OHAL also received interviews from filmmakers and graduate students that were added to the collection as distinct units. These materials, found in Series 2-9, are further described at the series level.
Hungarian Americans; Italian Americans.; Communism -- United States.; Anarchists -- United States -- Biography; Right and left (Political science).; Communists -- United States -- Interviews.; Yiddish newspapers; Yiddish literature.; Labor unions -- United States.; Labor union members -- United States -- Interviews.; Jewish radicals; Women employees -- United States; Women radicals -- United States -- Interviews; Labor -- United States.; Oral histories (literary works); African American radicals -- Interviews; Anarchism -- United States.; Slavic Americans; Socialism -- Connecticut -- Bridgeport (Conn.).; Socialism -- United States.; Socialists -- United States -- Biography; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American -- Interviews.; Student movements -- United States; Boggs, Grace Lee; Moore, Audley, 1898-1997; Baxandall, Rosalyn Fraad, 1939- -- Interviews; Sale, Kirkpatrick; Communist Party of the United States of America -- Interviews; Morning Freiheit Association; Draper, Hal -- Interviews; Deak, Zoltan; Dunayevskaya, Raya -- Interviews; Darcy, Samuel, 1905-; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence; Goldberg, Itshe; Glaberman, Martin -- Interviews; Gitlin, Todd; Berrigan, Daniel; James, C. L. R. (Cyril Lionel Robert), 1901-1989 -- Interviews; American Committee for Protection of Foreign Born; Berry, Abner -- Interviews; Buhle, Paul, 1944-; Boggs, James -- Interviews; Epstein, Melech -- Interviews; Young Communist League of the U.S.; Bloom, Jonathan; Prago, Ruth.; Lemisch, Bea; Seeger, Pete, 1919-2014; Trade Union Unity League (U.S.); De Leon, Solon, 1883-; Patterson, Louise Thompson, 1901-1999; Rawick, George P., 1929-; Johnson-Forest Tendency; Matteotti Club; Cowley, Malcolm, 1898-1989; Chernin, Rose -- Interviews; Kolehmainen, Mary -- Interviews; Johnson, Howard, 1915- -- Interviews; Breitman, George -- Interviews; Glotzer, Albert, 1908-1999. -- Interviews; Noṿiḳ, P., 1891-; International Labor Defense -- Interviews; Industrial Workers of the World -- Interviews; Harrington, Michael, 1928-1989 -- Interviews; Harap, Louis -- Interviews; Gellert, Hugo, 1892-1985 -- Interviews; Foner, Moe, 1915- -- Interviews; Foner, Henry -- Interviews; Workers Party (1940-1949) -- Interviews; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring -- Interviews; Weir, Stan -- nterviews; Weiss, Myra Tanner -- Interviews; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.) -- Interviews; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968 -- Interviews; Socialist Workers Party -- Interviews; Southern Negro Youth Congress -- Interviews; Rubinstein, Annette Teta, 1910-2007. -- Interviews; Socialist Party (U.S.) -- Interviews; Le Sueur, Meridel -- Interviews; Rodney, Lester, 1911-2009 -- Interviews; O'Connor, Harvey, 1897-1987 -- Interviews; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993 -- Interviews; McLevy, Jasper, 1878-1962 -- Interviews; McKinney, Ernest Rice, 1886-1984 -- Interviews; McGrath, Thomas, 1916-1990 -- Interviews; Magil, A. B. (Abraham Bernard), 1905-2003 -- Interviews; Kolehmainen, Mary
- Series I. Oral History of the American Left Main Series, 1940-2011
  - Minka Alesh, Oct 26, 1982; cuid1163
    Scope and Content Note
    Interview includes discussion of the SNPJ (Slovenska Narodna Podporna Jednota), a Slovenian mutual aid society. Alesh discusses the organisation's membership, the politics of Slovenian immigrants, and the activities of the women's lodge, of which she was president. Alesh also discusses her involvement in the millinery workers' union in Chicago, her role on the union's executive board, union organizing, and strikes. The interview also includes discussion of life in Slovenia and immigration, the Slovenian community in Chicago, the Socialist Party, Eugene Debs, and financial support for Tito and Yugoslavian relief during World War II. Interview focuses most heavily on the period between the 1900s-1920s.
    Interview by Paul Buhle.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 41 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Alesh)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 1)
  - Jose Alvarez, Mar 15, 1983; cuid1164
    Interview includes discussion of origins of Spanish-language Communist movement in Ybor City, Florida during the 1920s-1930s; community support of Communists and relation to surrounding communities during the 1930s-1940s; immigration from Spain, work in tobacco factories, and activities of unions during the 1920s-1940s; and Red Scare decimation of Ybor City Left during the 1950s. Also discussed is a meeting with Fidel Castro in the 1950s, before Cuban Revolution. Joseph Norrick was present for interview with Alvarez, and second cassette of interview also contains a segment of a different interview with Joseph and Ruth Norrick.
    Duartion: 87 minutes in two parts
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Alvarez 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 2 A-B)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Freda Hogan Ameringer, undated; cuid1165
    Phone interview taken to support review essay of Ameringer's book that Green intended to submit to The Nation. Interview includes discussion of Ameringer's background and left-wing newspapers including the Oklahoma Leader and American Guardian.
    Interview by James Green.
    Duration: 84 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Ameringer 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 81, Audiocassette 362 A)
  - Freda Hogan Ameringer, Dec 11, 1977; cuid1166
    Tapes begin with a narrative about Ameringer's life, the Oklahoma Leader and other newspapers, activism among miners, her socialist family, and the early socialist movement, followed by an interview.
    Duration: 79 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Ameringer 3-4)
    - Original Recording (Box 81, Audiocassette 362 B)
  - Freda Hogan Ameringer, Jul 24, 1981; cuid1167
    Interview by Jim Green.
    Duration: 146 minutes in two parts; Preservation note: second part has channel shifting, drop-outs, and significant volume fluctuation
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Ameringer 5-7)
    - Original Recording (Box 81, Audiocassette 362 C-D)
  - Vicky Amter, Feb 19, 1978; cuid1168
    Interview includes discussion of the Communist Party on the Lower East Side of New York City during the 1940s-1960s, conflicts with her Socialist father, experiences as Local 65 shop steward, the Jefferson School, harassment and isolation of CP in the 1950s, and reactions to emergence of the New Left.
    Interview by Jon Bloom.
    Duration: 80 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Amter 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 3)
  - Herbert Aptheker -- Transcript, 1976; cuid1169 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    Conversation includes discussion of college radicalism in 1930s, his MA thesis on Nat Turner, joining the Communist Party, academic life, and the Jefferson School.
    Interview by Debby Cohen.
  - Harry Aronek, Oct 25, 1978; cuid1170
    Interview covers the topics of immigration and the political and cultural activities of the New York Jewish community during the 1930s-1950s.
    Duration: 46 minutes in two parts
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Aronek 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 4 A-B)
  - Sam Ashare, Mar 30, 1983; cuid1171
    Interview by Dan Georgakas.
    Duration: 56 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Ashare 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 5)
  - Jacob Aspiz, Apr 7, 1980; cuid1172
    Interview includes discussion of the Los Angeles Jewish Left since the 1930s, the rise of anti-Nazi "front" across Jewish community and Communists' participation in it, the isolation of Jewish Left during Cold War, Aspiz's literary interests, and his involvement in the Yiddishe Kultur Farband as a senior citizen.
    Duration: 93 minutes in two parts; Preservation note: for part two, Side 2: The first 20 minutes is at a significantly lower volume
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Aspiz 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 6 A-B)
  - Ben Axelrod, Oct 4, 1979; cuid1173
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Axelrod 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 10, Audiocassette 391)
  - Stanley Banach, March 23, Apr 11, 1984; cuid1174
    Conversation includes discussion of neighborhood background in Providence during the 1950s, army life in Vietnam and Germany, radical influences, and his political philosophy and aspirations. The interview also covers union activity at Electric Boat/Quonset Point, Rhode Island, organizing drives, and union activity at Brown & Sharpe before and during the 1982 strike.
    Duration: 85 minutes in two parts
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Banach 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 7 A-B)
  - Eugene Barnett -- Transcript, 1940 - 1946; cuid1175 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    Interview covers the topics of the Industrial Workers of the World in the Northwest of the United States during the 1910s, West Virginia coal miners at turn of century, becoming a unionist, lumber work in Northwest, and repression in Centralia, Washington.
    Transcription of a radio broadcast from circa 1940.
  - Walter Barry, Oct 21, 1980 - Dec 4, 1980; cuid1176
    Interview covers Barry's boyhood and first labor experience in Endicott, New York, the Trade Union Unity League and United Electrical Workers District 4, and the Westinghouse elevator plant in Jersey City, New Jersey during the 1930s-1950s.
    Interview by Ruth F. Prago.
    Duration: 137 minutes in three parts
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Barry 1-3)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 9A-C)
  - Irving Barshop, Oct 12, 1973; cuid1177
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Barshop 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 80, Audiocassette 334)
  - Rosalyn Baxandall, Nov 8, 1983; cuid1178
    Interview includes a discussion of the differences between Baxandall's expectations and the realities of left wing culture at the University of Wisconsin-Madison from 1958 through the 1960s, after coming from New York Old Left background and having a brief stint at Smith College. Also discussed are gender relations in the left and academy; the relationship between music, poetry, theatre, and beat culture and politics in Madison; and the importance of the Rathskeller bar in academic and radical life. Baxandall also discusses her studies in French and history, academic role models, challenging cultural norms, the beginnings of the women's movement in Madison, and the impact of her time at Madison on the rest of her life.
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Baxandall 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 10)
  - Bertha Bazell, Mar 10, 1981; cuid1179
    Interview covers Bazell's immigrant Jewish background, the Workmen's Circle, involvement in the Communist Party during the 1930s-1950s in Coney Island, New York and later in Fall River, Massachusetts. It also addresses harassment of left wingers by the FBI during the the 1950s.
    Interview by Bill Schecter.
    Duration: 52 minutes
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Bazell 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 11)
  - Irving Beinin, Jul 2, 1988; cuid1180
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Beinin 1)
    - Original Recording (Box 79, Audiocassette 292)
  - Ray and Rose Bell, Aug 2, 1985; cuid1181
    Topics discussed include working class life and union organizing in textile mills.
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Bell 1-3)
    - Original Recording (Box 10, Audiocassette 415 A-C)
    - Transcript (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Fay Bennett, May 26, 1983; cuid1182
    Interview covers the college anti-war movement during the 1930s, the American Student Union, Keep America Out of War Congress during the late 1930s, the experience of conscientious objectors during World War II, and postwar work with National Sharecroppers' Fund.
    Duration: 66 minutes in two parts
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Bennett 1-2)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 12 A-B)
  - Jack Bergen -- Transcript, 1967; cuid1183 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    Interview covers Bridgeport, Connecticut during the 1910s, life during the Great Depression, Bridgeport mayor Jasper McLevy, and the Socialist Party in Connecticut state politics during the 1930s.
    Interview by Bruce Stave.
  - John T. Bernard, Jun 25, 1977; cuid1184
    Recording of a Mesaba Park Cooperative Association tribute to John Bernard, a Farmer-Labor Party representative from Minnesota's Eighth Congressional District, who served from 1936-1938. It includes speeches by former Minnesota Governor Elmer Benson and others about Bernard's record in Congress, a response from Bernard, and music.
    Duration: 158 minutes in three parts
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Bernard 1-5)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 14 A-C)
  - Daniel Berrigan, Apr 1, 1970; cuid1185
    This recording was Berrigan's last interview before he went underground and then to prison. It includes reflections on his activities during the 1960s, including the Catonsville incident.
    Interview by Marc Weiss.
    - Access Copy (Box 11, Cd Berrigan 1-3)
    - Original Recording (Box 1, Audiocassette 15 A-C)
  - Abner Berry, 1974-1977; cuid1186
    Interview describes the Communist Party in Harlem during the 1930s, including his involvement in Communist Party apparatus, personalities in the CP, relationships with other activist groups, and the CP's intellectual climate during the Great Depression.